<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Longreads Blog</title>
	<atom:link href="https://blog.longreads.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://blog.longreads.com</link>
	<description>The best longform stories on the web</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2016 04:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='blog.longreads.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/e68667ec6ee7cdd0c6b5416a84c52a9c?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs2.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>Longreads Blog</title>
		<link>https://blog.longreads.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://blog.longreads.com/osd.xml" title="Longreads Blog" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://blog.longreads.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>All Hail the Queen: Five Stories About Pageants</title>
		<link>https://blog.longreads.com/2016/09/10/all-hail-the-queen-five-stories-about-pageants/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2016 03:58:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Emily Perper]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reading List]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[BuzzFeed]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jezebel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[longreads]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Hairpin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vice]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.longreads.com/?p=39241</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this list, you'll find stories about drag royalty, the price of the perfect Western wardrobe, the perils of butt glue, and more.<img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39241&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On Sunday, the first openly gay Miss America contestant will vie for the crown on national TV. She&#8217;s Miss Missouri, Erin O&#8217;Flaherty, and her platform centers on suicide prevention—a particularly prescient topic, since LGBTQ-identified teens are far more likely to attempt suicide than their straight peers. I&#8217;m excited for O&#8217;Flaherty and hopeful her presence will increase awareness of the abysmal suicide rates among our community. On the other hand, I take issue with O&#8217;Flaherty&#8217;s <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/miss-america-erin-oflaherty_us_57d1a14de4b06a74c9f35da4?">declaration</a> that &#8220;the Miss America Organization has always been open and accepting of women of all backgrounds.&#8221; This, as I learned during my reading this week, is simply not true. Black women were prohibited from competing until 1950. Women who had abortions or were divorced could not compete until 1999. Until recently, the &#8220;swimwear&#8221; modeling portion accounted for 15 percent of each contestant&#8217;s overall score; this year, it&#8217;s <a href="http://www.pressofatlanticcity.com/missamerica/swimsuits-live-on-in-miss-america-pageant-but-for-how/article_e80e6a72-6e2b-11e6-ae5c-4bddd8d72996.html">10 percent</a>. These are just the facts.</p>
<p>Miss America isn&#8217;t the only pageant out there, of course, and this week, I learned about Miss Rodeo America and Miss Gay America, too. In this list, you&#8217;ll find stories about drag royalty, the price of the perfect Western wardrobe, the perils of butt glue, and more. <span id="more-39241"></span></p>
<h2>1. <a href="https://maryreview.com/miss-america/">&#8220;Through the Looking Glass.&#8221;</a> (Kathleen Hale, Mary Review, September 2016)</h2>
<p>I can&#8217;t wait to read everything from Mary Review, a newish publication dedicated to spotlighting the work of women. Kathleen Hale catalogues the week she spent in Atlantic City in 2015, watching the Miss America contestants compete, eating $6 pretzels, bonding with her fellow catty audience members and wrestling with her own self-image.</p>
<h2>2. <a href="https://www.buzzfeed.com/tylergillespie/drag-queens-of-the-bible-belt?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Longform%20830&amp;utm_content=Longform%20830+CID_d6d188ec6ffb38ec76e7ee1e0c0bb665&amp;utm_source=BuzzFeed%20Newsletters&amp;utm_term=.pcx4qblkD#.yvp3VbX2r">&#8220;Drag Queens of the Bible Belt.&#8221;</a> (Tyler Gillespie, BuzzFeed LGBT, August 2015)</h2>
<p>The first Miss Gay America winner was from Arkansas, and Tyler Gillespie travels to Arkansas to observe the 44th annual Miss Gay Arkansas pageant. It&#8217;s collaborative, historical, and beautiful:</p>
<blockquote><p>When [Jonathan] Neighbors performs as Blaze, she puts on makeup for a pageant by taking pieces from her drag family’s styles — the way they paint or dress — and mixes them to tell their family story. Her drag sisters have shared secrets like different ways to apply makeup and how to dress for her body. She paints a family portrait on her own face. In most cases, drag mothers choose their drag daughters, and this relationship is not only an extension of family but one similar to classical apprenticeship. A daughter learns techniques from a skilled artist as would any fledgling painter.</p></blockquote>
<h2>3. <a href="http://jezebel.com/a-night-in-atlantic-city-for-miss-americas-95th-birthda-1730494580">&#8220;A Night in Atlantic City for Miss America&#8217;s 95th Birthday.&#8221;</a> (Kate Dries, Jezebel, September 2015)</h2>
<p>Katie Dries&#8217; piece for Jezebel is the perfect complement to Kathleen Hale&#8217;s essay at Mary Review. In particular, Dries delves into the finances of Miss America&#8217;s scholarship program and its small-town, insular vibe.</p>
<h2>4. <a href="https://thehairpin.com/bess-myerson-the-first-jewish-miss-america-ec0600798b4#.v0g9rclu9">&#8220;Bess Myerson, the First Jewish Miss America.&#8221;</a> (EJ Dickson, The Hairpin, June 2015)</h2>
<p>Last week, during a late-night Pinterest bender, I searched &#8220;big nose&#8221; and &#8220;wide nose.&#8221; The result? Contouring tutorials, when all I wanted was to see someone who looked kinda like me: half-Jewish, with a nose not long but wide, out of proportion to the rest of my face, in a way I&#8217;ve come to accept and appreciate (mostly). Apparently, I should be contouring. I proceeded to ramble on my private blog about hotness and desirability. Alas. Even though our circumstances are different, I can appreciate EJ Dickson&#8217;s essay on wanting to see Jewish women represented in beauty pageantry—a.k.a. sexually desirable—and her joy upon discovering the first Jewish Miss America, Bess Myerson. Sometimes you just want to world to tell you you&#8217;re pretty. It&#8217;s not very feminist, but I know that feeling well. I commend Dickson for her honesty.</p>
<h2>5. <a href="https://medium.com/matter/rodeo-queens-of-the-west-9bcfb7fa8911#.usq4yev3w">&#8220;Queens of the West.&#8221;</a> (Gabriela Herman, Matter, October 2014)</h2>
<p class="graf--p graf-after--p _RIL_KEEPER_CLASS_">Welcome to Miss Rodeo America. Unless you win, you&#8217;re done queening&#8211;forever.</p>
<blockquote><p>Whoever walks away with the crown — a Black Hills gold, pearl, and Alexandrite band that sits atop a cowboy hat — will travel the world. She’ll get $20,000 in scholarship money, plus cowboy hats worth $10,000 from her sponsors. She’ll get custom boots, buckles with her name engraved in silver, and more. She’ll meet and shake hands with thousands, including agribusiness CEOs, senators, and a wide swath of America’s conservative, rural elite.</p>
<p id="ddf4" class="graf--p graf--startsWithDoubleQuote graf-after--p _RIL_KEEPER_CLASS_">“Every second — every second — you have to be perfect and look perfect while you’re doing it,” Nicole [Schrock] said. “People that don’t know anything about the rodeo will come up to you and say something offensive and you just have to smile and keep on going… sometimes, people have meltdowns.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p><img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39241&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
		
		<media:thumbnail url="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/16260674029_74553fea1f_o.jpg" />
		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/16260674029_74553fea1f_o.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">16260674029_74553fea1f_o</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/50bd3faf41be155829d0abf3b8b02119?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">emilyperper</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Top 5 Longreads of the Week</title>
		<link>https://blog.longreads.com/2016/09/09/the-top-5-longreads-of-the-week-135/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 19:50:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Longreads]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reading List]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Top 5]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[longreads]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reading list]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top 5]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.longreads.com/?p=39336</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Our top stories of the week, as chosen by the editors at Longreads.<img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39336&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Below, our favorite stories of the week.</em></p>
<p><em><a href="http://longreads.us2.list-manage2.com/subscribe?u=1854296747731744c923a33ef&amp;id=bd2ad42066">Sign up to receive this list free every Friday in your inbox.</a></em><span id="more-39336"></span></p>
<p style="text-align:center;">* * *</p>
<h2 class="top5-title"><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/news/2016/09/elizabeth-holmes-theranos-exclusive" target="_blank">1. How Elizabeth Holmes&#039;s House of Cards Came Tumbling Down</a></h2>
<p class="top5-credit"><em>Nick Bilton | Vanity Fair&nbsp;| Sept. 6, 2016 | 14&nbsp;minutes (5,119&nbsp;words)</em></p>
<p style="text-align:left;">At once-lauded biotech start-up Theranos, Elizabeth Holmes built a multi-billion-dollar corporation on a foundation of questionable science and secrecy.</p>
<h2 class="top5-title"><a href="http://www.esquire.com/news-politics/a47390/alabama-isis-peyton-pruitt/" target="_blank">2. The FBI Accused Him of Terrorism. He Couldn&#039;t Tie His Shoes.</a></h2>
<p class="top5-credit"><em>Jessica Pishko | Esquire&nbsp;| Sept. 8, 2016 | 51 minutes (3,722&nbsp;words)</em></p>
<p>A disabled 18-year-old named Peyton Pruitt, who functions at the level of an 8-year-old child, is accused of becoming an ISIS recruit.</p>
<h2 class="top5-title"><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2016/09/12/the-ayahuasca-boom-in-the-u-s?src=longreads" target="_blank">3. The Drug of Choice for the Age of Kale</a></h2>
<p class="top5-credit"><em>Ariel Levy | The New Yorker&nbsp;| Sept. 5, 2016 | 21&nbsp;minutes (5,413&nbsp;words) </em></p>
<p>The ancient South American hallucinogen ayahuasca has become America&#039;s psychedelic drug du jour, with everyone from Baby Boomers and Millennials to the Silicon Valley set seeking its potent revelations about harmony and interspecies unity. To hear the plants speak, all you need is money and some strength of mind.</p>
<h2 class="top5-title"><a href="http://www.elle.com/life-love/a39035/death-abusive-father/" target="_blank">4. My Father Was an Abusive Sociopath, And I Was the Only One He Had Left</a></h2>
<p class="top5-credit"><em>Christina Wallace | Elle | Sept. 8, 2016 | 17&nbsp;minutes (4,328&nbsp;words) </em></p>
<p>Christina Wallace&#039;s devastating essay about being called upon to place into a nursing home the sociopathic father she hadn&rsquo;t seen in years&mdash;who&rsquo;d molested her, and beaten her mother&mdash;and to then attend his funeral.</p>
<h2 class="top5-title"><a href="http://www.eater.com/2016/9/7/12815714/coke-coca-cola-first-history" target="_blank">5. The 24-Year-Old Coca-Cola Virgin</a></h2>
<p class="top5-credit"><em>Jamie Lauren Keiles | Eater&nbsp;|&nbsp;Sept. 7, 2016 | 22&nbsp;minutes (5,573&nbsp;words)</em></p>
<p>&quot;If you&rsquo;re looking for evidence of mass commonality, it doesn&rsquo;t come cheaper or more convenient than Coke. It&rsquo;s consumed around 1.9 billion times per day, and distributed everywhere except North Korea and Cuba (for now). Through Coke we all have something in common &mdash; Liz Taylor knows it, the president knows it, the bum knows it, and you know it. I, on the other hand, can only trust and speculate. I&rsquo;ve never had a Coke in my life.&quot;</p><img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39336&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
		
		<media:thumbnail url="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/14996838579_c545449611_k.jpg" />
		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/14996838579_c545449611_k.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">14996838579_c545449611_k</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/77c994c441138efdb7338403caac1014?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">longreadseditors</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Revisiting the Ghosts of Attica</title>
		<link>https://blog.longreads.com/2016/09/09/revisiting-the-ghosts-of-attica/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 12:12:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tom Robbins]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attica prison riot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[longreads]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marshall project collaboration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Marshall Project]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tom Robbins]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.longreads.com/?p=39323</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A wrenching new book recounts the bloodiest prison battle in our history.<img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39323&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align:center;"><em><a href="https://twitter.com/tommy_robb">Tom Robbins</a> | <a href="https://www.themarshallproject.org/">The Marshall Project</a> | September 2016 | 22 minutes (3,722 words)</em></p>
<div class="publisher-intro"><a href="http://www.themarshallproject.org/" target="_blank"><img class="publisher-intro-cover" style="height:56px;" src="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/marshall-project-icon.png?w=728" alt="The Marshall Project" /></a><span class="publisher-intro-text">This story was co-published with <a href="http://www.themarshallproject.org/" target="_blank">The Marshall Project</a>, a nonprofit news organization covering the U.S. criminal justice system. Sign up for their <a href="https://www.themarshallproject.org/subscribe" target="_blank">newsletter</a>, or follow The Marshall Project on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/TheMarshallProject.org" target="_blank">Facebook</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/MarshallProj" target="_blank">Twitter</a>.</span></div>
<p>On the morning of September 13, 1971, shortly after state police launched an armed assault to retake Attica prison from its rebelling inmates, a trooper emptied his .357 magnum pistol into a prisoner named Kenneth B. Malloy. As Heather Ann Thompson recounts in her wrenching and minutely detailed recounting of that day, Malloy’s death was one of the most hideous on a morning of hideous deeds, one that saw 39 people killed by police, another 89 wounded. Malloy, an autopsy later showed, was shot twelve times at close range by at least two guns. He was hit with so many bullets, Thompson reports, “that his eye sockets were shredded by the shards of his own bones.”</p>
<p>Not far away, an inmate named James Robinson was fatally wounded with a .270 caliber bullet fired by a police rifle. As he lay dying, another trooper stepped up and finished him off, firing a load of buckshot into Robinson’s neck. Afterward, a police sergeant snapped a photo of Robinson, who, like many inmates, had donned a football helmet in feeble hope of warding off the baton blows they imagined were the worst they might suffer in the retaking. His body lay splayed on its side, a state police tag looped around his empty right hand. A second photo, taken moments later, shows Robinson in precisely the same position, except that a curved sword has now appeared beside him. The trooper who shot him later insisted he did so because the inmate had charged him with such a weapon.</p>
<div data-shortcode="caption" id="attachment_39333" style="width: 211px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Blood-Water-Attica-Prison-Uprising/dp/0375423222?tag=longreads-20"><img src="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/d1n0c1ufntxbvh-cloudfront.jpg?w=201&#038;h=300" alt="“Blood in the Water: The Attica Prison Uprising of 1971 and Its Legacy,” Heather Ann Thompson, Pantheon Books 2016 KNOPF DOUBLEDAY" width="201" height="300" class="size-medium wp-image-39333" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">“Blood in the Water: The Attica Prison Uprising of 1971 and Its Legacy,” Heather Ann Thompson, Pantheon Books 2016 KNOPF DOUBLEDAY</p></div>
<p>The name Attica still registers dread and sorrow in Americans old enough to recall that drizzly and blood-flecked week at the upstate New York prison. No matter who you blamed for the carnage, the slaughter that gray September morning in a tiny rural hamlet thirty-five miles east of Buffalo, a place few had ever heard of, evoked anguish and fury. Photos and film clips of raincoat-clad troopers stepping through the mud amidst tangles of dead and wounded men, of long snaking lines of inmates stripped naked, their hands atop their heads, settled deep into the marrow of those who saw them. Charles Mingus and John Lennon set music to the tragedy. Muhammad Ali composed a fierce bit of doggerel that he read on TV: &#8220;Better than of this prison rot / If there&#8217;s any chance I&#8217;ve got / Kill me here on this spot.&#8221;</p>
<p>Even those innocent of any knowledge of the riot and the rage it inspired, can still recognize its incantatory power in Sidney Lumet’s 1975 “Dog Day Afternoon,” as Al Pacino riles up a crowd outside the Brooklyn bank he is robbing by crying out, &#8220;Attica! Attica!&#8221; <span id="more-39323"></span></p>
<p>Almost all of those killed in what was then a mind-boggling body count died in the span of a less than a quarter of an hour as state troopers, correction officers and sheriff’s deputies, under a thick fog of pepper gas, directed a withering fire from rifles and pistols at rebelling inmates who had held the facility for four days. The McKay Commission, the first of several state panels appointed to investigate the riot, hauntingly described it as the “bloodiest one-day encounter between Americans” since the Civil War and the Indian massacres of the late 19<sup>th</sup> century. Unlike those conflicts, however, only one side had guns at Attica.</p>
<p>The police assault came after Governor Nelson Rockefeller, whose decade-old presidential ambitions were still burning brightly in 1971, refused to come to the scene to help resolve the standoff, despite pleadings to do so by some of his own Republican allies. The surge was supposed to be a rescue operation as well as a recapture of the facility. As such it was an appalling failure: Ten of those slain by police bullets were state employees, guards and civilian staff who had been held as hostages since September 9<sup>th</sup> when inmates first seized the prison. Several other hostages were grievously wounded.</p>
<p>After state officials surveyed the scene, they went outside and told waiting reporters perhaps the most nefarious lie ever uttered by American public servants: The hostages had been murdered by the inmates, they said, their throats slit. Another had been castrated. Within hours, the story was around the world. None of it was true.</p>
<p>All of that grim history is tellingly replayed in “Blood in the Water.” A professor of history at the University of Michigan, Thompson spent thirteen years excavating the ruins of what remains America’s most deadly prison riot. Her trail took her through investigative files, voluminous court dockets, the testimony of survivors, as well as the recordings of phone conversations as Rockefeller kept Richard Nixon and the White House abreast of events during the siege. Both men were convinced the uprising was part of a vast radical conspiracy, ranging from anti-war protests to the Black Panthers. “The whole thing was led by the blacks,” Rockefeller told Nixon after the prison had been retaken. “We’ll do the mopping up now.”</p>
<p>In fact, as Thompson makes clear, while radical views inspired many of the leaders, the rebellion’s roots lay in the many daily indignities of prison life: lack of showers, insufficient toilet paper, inadequate medical care and the near-constant disrespect expressed by many of their keepers. As for Rockefeller’s benign sounding “mop-up,” it was as gruesome and criminal, if not as deadly, as the opening salvo of police guns: Thompson reports that one inmate was sodomized with a Phillips screwdriver; others had plasma tubes ripped from their arms and lit cigarettes tossed onto their chests. All were forced, after crawling face down through the muck, to run a gauntlet of club-swinging guards while barefoot and over broken glass.</p>
<p>Such terrors were not completely one-sided: After the assault, officers found the mangled corpses of three other prisoners, slain by the inmates themselves during the takeover.</p>
<p>John Cudmore, a physician in the National Guard who tried to attend to the many injured that day, told his wife late that night that he now “understood how the massacre at My Lai had happened.”</p>
<p>Part of the strength of “Blood in the Water” is the many pungent details Thompson paints into her portrait of the central event. Some are moments of farce: As the riot was erupting, with fires already burning, an inmate in the prison laundry picked up a ringing telephone to hear the warden’s wife ordering clean bed linens for the large brick mansion on the hill next door to the prison where she and her family resided. At least that phone worked. When a guard at Times Square, the prison’s central hub where the riot broke out, tried to call for help the line was dead.</p>
<p>Others are of horror: in the first minutes of the riot, two inmates &#8211; brothers &#8211; were seized by a clutch of predatory prisoners and repeatedly raped in a bathroom. There are also heroics: Leaders of the uprising, many of them later singled out for retribution by guards, braved the wrath of their fellow inmates by guiding at least eleven injured hostages to safety. Among them was correction officer William Quinn, whose death two days later from the beating he took as the riot began was to hugely complicate negotiations aimed at resolving the siege.</p>
<p>And there is awe: One elderly inmate stood in D Yard the first night of the occupation and stared at the sky. It was the first time, he said, that he’d “seen the stars in twenty-two years.”</p>
<div data-shortcode="caption" id="attachment_39329" style="width: 738px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img src="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/ap_64693233018.jpg?w=728&#038;h=556" alt="Inmates of the Attica Correctional Facility negotiating with Russell G. Oswald, lower left, the state prisons commissioner, in September 1971. ASSOCIATED PRESS" width="728" height="556" class="size-large wp-image-39329" /><p class="wp-caption-text">Inmates of the Attica Correctional Facility negotiating with Russell G. Oswald, lower left, the state prisons commissioner, in September 1971. ASSOCIATED PRESS</p></div>
<p>This is the Attica tragedy with which most are familiar, a massive bloodletting marked by spasms of sadism. Thompson chose for her title the image of the blood that glistened in pools of rainwater in the ditches inmates had dug in vain to protect themselves. But it’s no coincidence that so many earlier works about the riot and its aftermath have invoked the word “ghosts.” “You probably don’t believe in ghosts,” Elizabeth Gaynes, a lawyer who defended inmates charged with crimes after the riot told me in an interview a couple of years ago. “But I do. The ghosts there won’t go away.”</p>
<p>Ghosts linger, of course, where terrible crimes have been left unresolved, and few places are as filled with as much ghastly and unpunished wrongdoing as Attica. After the riot, the state vigorously pursued convictions against inmates for crimes including murder, kidnapping and conspiracy. In exchange for paroles, some inmates agreed to testify in those cases, although most ultimately admitted they were just guessing when it came to identifying defendants. Thompson cites one prisoner who tried to name a perpetrator of one of the vicious murders carried out before the assault. The investigator wasn’t interested, however. The only suspects he wanted to hear about, he said, were leaders of the uprising.</p>
<p>There was substantially less enthusiasm for making cases against law enforcement officials. Only one police officer was ever charged, for reckless endangerment. And that indictment, along with the other convictions and pending charges, was wiped away in 1976 by a new governor, Hugh Carey, who pardoned all involved saying he wanted to “close the books.”</p>
<p>That’s the other, less familiar, tragedy of Attica, and Thompson takes that part of the story a major step further than previous accounts, by naming some of the officers, state police as well as correction guards, who, at one point, faced potentially serious charges by grand juries.</p>
<p>To explain how and why those juries stopped short of indictments, Thompson draws heavily on Malcolm Bell, the whistle-blowing former special prosecutor who presented much of the evidence to the panels, before his bosses ordered him to stand down. Bell eventually resigned, taking his tale of obstruction to New York Times columnist Tom Wicker, who had gone through his own searing experience as one of the outside observers during the riot (and who wrote one of great books of participatory journalism about it, “A Time to Die.”) Wicker brought in investigative reporter Myron Farber whose stories appeared on the Times’ front pages in April, 1975.</p>
<div data-shortcode="caption" id="attachment_39332" style="width: 210px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img src="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/51jdxpa2axl.jpg?w=200&#038;h=300" alt="“The Turkey Shoot: Tracking the Attica Cover-up,” by Malcolm Bell, foreword by Tom Wicker, Grove Press 1985 (scheduled for re-release in March, 2017, with a new introduction and epilogue by the author as “The Attica Turkey Shoot: Justice On Trial.”) (pictured) SKYHORSE PUBLISHING" width="200" height="300" class="size-medium wp-image-39332" /><p class="wp-caption-text">“The Turkey Shoot: Tracking the Attica Cover-up,” by Malcolm Bell, foreword by Tom Wicker, Grove Press 1985 (scheduled for re-release in March, 2017, with a new introduction and epilogue by the author as “The Attica Turkey Shoot: Justice On Trial.”) (pictured) SKYHORSE PUBLISHING</p></div>
<p>Bell’s own account, “The Turkey Shoot: Tracking the Attica Cover-up,” is to be reissued early next year. In the small canon of whistleblower literature, the book is a classic, a kind of nonfiction police procedural whose protagonist is initially overwhelmed by doubts and confusion, only to be filled with outrage once he realizes that justice has been purposely thwarted. A Republican who voted for Nixon in 1968, Bell found himself, by the end of his brief stint as a special prosecutor, pondering possible conspiracies reaching into both Albany’s executive mansion and the White House.</p>
<p>Given what he learned in his digging, such notions weren’t much of a stretch. Police had taken purposeful steps to obscure who did what that day, Bell found. Before storming the prison, police commanders ordered officers to remove their name tags. And although standard policy called for a record to be made of which weapons were issued to which officers, no one kept track when rifles were handed out to troopers. Also ignored was a requirement that officers fill out reports detailing the number of times they had discharged their weapons and why. When Bell pressed senior police officials about why no such reports were compiled after Attica he was told, with a straight face, that the reports were used only when officers had shot at animals.</p>
<p>The absence of such records helped frustrate efforts by prosecutors to tie shootings to specific shooters. More frustrations arose when investigators finally received a cache of photos and film footage of the retaking that had been taken by police. Pictures that should have captured officers in the act of firing on slain inmates were oddly missing, as though the cameras had turned away at crucial moments. Actually, the cover-up was cruder than that: When an investigator peeled back the cardboard corners of the Kodak slides the police provided, he found gaps in the numbering, breaks that corresponded to shootings that were likely crimes. But at least many photos were handed over. Logs and tapes of radio messages between police during the retaking somehow went missing altogether.</p>
<p>Among the missing slides, Bell and investigators noted, were those that would likely have recorded two of the most blatant inmate executions that morning, the shootings of Malloy and Robinson. In his own book, Bell scrupulously kept to his oath of grand jury secrecy, referring to his chief suspects only as “Trooper A” and “Trooper B” etc. But as part of his effort to press state officials to continue the probe, Bell wrote a lengthy memo to Carey after his 1974 election in which he laid out the specifics of the “shooter” cases he had been presenting to the grand jury, as well as broader “hindering prosecution” charges he had expected to bring against high level state police officials involved in the cover-up.</p>
<p>This memo, including the names of suspects, was one of those that surfaced during Thompson’s own painstaking search, when a court clerk in upstate Erie County mistakenly gave her access to sealed records. This is the kind of kismet that researchers live for, and unsurprisingly, Thompson has included much of the memos, along with the names of the suspects, in her book.</p>
<p>Her revelations are even more notable since they come just one year after a much-publicized bid by relatives of hostages and New York state attorney general Eric Schneiderman to win release of two previously secret volumes compiled by one of the state panels that investigated the riot. A judge in Erie County agreed to unseal the volumes, but ordered that all grand jury information be redacted.</p>
<p>Bell, who is otherwise admiring and supportive of Thompson’s accomplishment, even helping to fact-check the manuscript, said he disapproved of her decision to name names. “The memos were works in progress in many cases,” he told me from his home in Vermont last month. “They were not the end of the story.” As examples, Bell cited two individuals whom he said were incorrectly named as shooting suspects in the book. But he acknowledged that the book was “probably right about who the shooter was” in other instances.</p>
<p>As it happens, many of the suspects’ names were not all that secret. Stories in upstate New York papers in the late 1970s and early ‘80s about the criminal and civil litigation that followed in the wake of the riot included the names of many of those cited in Thompson’s book as suspects. As early as December, 1975, the Rochester Democrat &amp; Chronicle reported that seven officers had been cleared of crimes committed at Attica by the grand jury. According to Bell, those votes to “no bill” the suspects came after his former supervisors rushed his unfinished cases through in a bid to minimize the public embarrassment stemming from the Times articles about the cover-up.</p>
<p>Whatever the reason, among those the newspaper reported had been cleared was New York State Trooper James R. Mittelstaedt, the man alleged to have fired the shotgun blast that finished off an already dying James Robinson, according to “Blood in the Water.” Mittelstaedt, the newspaper article stated, was cleared of four counts, including second-degree murder and first-degree manslaughter.</p>
<p>Even more details appeared concerning one of the former officers alleged to have shot Kenneth B. Malloy, the inmate whose eyes were obliterated by bullets. In July, 1981, the Democrat &amp; Chronicle and other papers covered testimony at a hearing for a civil lawsuit filed by the widow of one of the slain hostages. There, a state police captain testified that a trooper under his command named Aldo Barbolini had used his own .357-caliber revolver to shoot an inmate. The article noted that Malloy was the only victim killed by .357-caliber bullets. State police captain James Patterson testified that Barbolini told him he had “shot a Negro” at least three times. Trooper Barbolini had initially lied, Patterson said, claiming that he had retrieved a shotgun from the slain inmate, a rifle that he then used to kill another prisoner who was cowering in one of the trenches inmates had dug. He later admitted he had borrowed the shotgun from another trooper.</p>
<p>State police officials were sufficiently alarmed about Barbolini’s actions that they told him he could resign or face criminal charges. On September 17, just four days after the assault, Barbolini tendered his resignation. But none of that was ever relayed to Bell or the investigators trying to determine culpability in the deaths of Malloy and others. Barbolini, however, court records show, refused to go away quietly. In 1977, after Carey announced his pardons, he filed suit seeking reinstatement, claiming that he had been wrongly coerced into his resignation. A court ruled he had waited too long to file his suit.</p>
<p>Thompson has said she did not contact those named in the prosecutorial memos for fear that they might take legal steps to block her book’s publication. In many cases, including that of Trooper Mittelstaedt, she needn’t have worried. After retiring from the state police, Mittelstaedt died in 2005 of kidney failure. His obituary noted that he had been “among the legion of officers” that helped take back control of Attica after the uprising. In retirement, he had taught criminal justice at a local community college.</p>
<p>Aldo Barbolini, however, is still with us. After he failed to get his job back with the state police, he served as a postmaster in Highland Falls, N.Y., and worked part-time at the Palisades Interstate Park Commission. Subpoenaed as a witness in 1991 in a lawsuit brought by former Attica inmates, Barbolini took the Fifth Amendment forty-four times. He retired to Florida in 2001 with a small state pension. He did not respond to numerous messages last month.</p>
<p>“Blood in the Water” reminds one generation, and informs others, that this willful failure to pursue justice for the victims of Attica remains one of the bleakest, if least acknowledged, chapters in New York history. That cycle of killing, torture and cover-up all happened not in some backward, faraway place, but in a deep blue state.</p>
<p>New York’s dismal performance is brightened only slightly by efforts made in the wake of the riot to respond to some of the inmates’ grievances. Officials did so, Thompson makes clear in her epilogue, out of recognition that the men and women they were locking away for years needed to believe they had some means of being heard. It was either that or risk more uprisings. To that end, in addition to basics such as more showers, soap, medical care and family visits, officials introduced some of the rudiments of fairness the rebels had demanded: For the first time, inmates were allowed to elect a liaison committee to speak for them; a grievance procedure, complete with hearings, was enacted. A statewide network of lawyers to assist inmates, Prisoners Legal Services, received funding. Access to higher education was made available.</p>
<p>For a time, those changes helped ameliorate some of the prison system’s worst failings. But it wasn’t long before those modest reforms were swamped in the surging tide of new prisoners swept into the system by the draconian new drug statutes that Rockefeller introduced in 1973 in one more bid to be accepted by national leaders of his party as a true law and order Republican. That plan succeeded for Rockefeller when Gerald Ford picked him as vice president a year later. It proved a disaster for thousands of New Yorkers, however. It is stunning to reflect that at the time of the Attica riot, the state’s prison population was all of 12,500. By 1999, that number had grown to 72,600. Today, eight years after Rockefeller’s drug laws were finally rolled back, the population is 52,000.</p>
<p>Forty-five years after the uprising, Attica’s ghosts remain palpable behind its soaring walls. A granite marker outside the front gate lists the names of the employees who died. Those of the inmates who perished, almost three times in number, are nowhere to be found. The racial disparity between the keepers and the kept remains as stark as it was then. At the time of the riot, there was a single Hispanic among 500 guards, while 63 percent of the prisoners were minority; today, 80 percent of the prisoners are black or Hispanic, and while there are 100 more guards than in 1971, less than two dozen are minorities.</p>
<p>Last year, three guards there pleaded guilty to having beaten an inmate so badly he needed surgery to repair one of his broken legs. Yet the sanction they received was the same as Kenneth Malloy’s executor: they had to quit their jobs. Still, it was the first time officers had been criminally charged for such an incident, and when I went to Attica to talk to inmates about it they told me their only surprise was that word of the beating had reached beyond the prison’s walls. Such incidents were common, they said. Most despaired of winning outside help. Perhaps another riot was the answer, they said.</p>
<div data-shortcode="caption" id="attachment_39331" style="width: 210px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Uprising-Understanding-Attica-Revolution-Incarceration-ebook/dp/B005L393WW?tag=longreads-20"><img src="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/51bdfcba19l.jpg?w=200&#038;h=300" alt="Uprising: Understanding Attica, Revolution and the Incarceration State, Clarence B. Jones and Stuart Connelly, Kindle Books 2011. AMAZON" width="200" height="300" class="size-medium wp-image-39331" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Uprising: Understanding Attica, Revolution and the Incarceration State, Clarence B. Jones and Stuart Connelly, Kindle Books 2011. AMAZON</p></div>
<p>One of those still haunted by Attica’s ghosts is Clarence B. Jones, the former Amsterdam News publisher who had earlier served as a lawyer and advisor to Martin Luther King, Jr. When the riot broke out, Jones was summoned to Attica by Rockefeller himself to join Wicker, radical attorney William Kunstler and others requested by the inmates to aid negotiations with state officials. In his short book, Uprising, Jones writes that the last time he had spoken with Rockefeller prior to Attica was in 1963 when the governor had, secretly, given him $100,000 in cash to help bail out King and others jailed during the Birmingham civil rights protests. For political reasons, the governor didn’t want his generosity known. But Jones hardly viewed him as racist.</p>
<p>The day before the assault, however, he personally pleaded with Rockefeller to come to the prison. The governor, coldly and crisply, Jones recalls, simply thanked him “for his service.” That night, in an interview with David Frost on CBS, Jones said “The hands of the Governor of the State of New York are dripping with blood.” After the show aired, Rockefeller called him at home to say he understood Jones’ anger. “You did what you had to do. I did what I had to do as governor,” Rockefeller told him.</p>
<p>“Those people were under your care,” Jones responded.</p>
<p>“You can’t save everyone, Mr. Jones,” the governor replied.</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">* * *</p>
<p style="text-align:center;"><em><a href="https://twitter.com/tommy_robb">Tom Robbins</a> has been a columnist and staff writer at the Village Voice, the New York Daily News, and The New York Observer. Since 2011, he has been investigative journalist in residence at the City University of New York Graduate School of Journalism. His series on prison violence in New York, produced in collaboration with The Marshall Project and The New York Times, was named a 2016 Pulitzer Prize finalist for Investigative Reporting and won the 2016 Hillman Prize for Newspaper Journalism.</em></p><img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39323&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
		
		<media:thumbnail url="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/ap_396668511721.jpg" />
		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/ap_396668511721.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Attica Whistleblower</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/5f25380be8b23bff144531fe0a0b5fcc?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">tommyrobb</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/marshall-project-icon.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">The Marshall Project</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/d1n0c1ufntxbvh-cloudfront.jpg?w=201" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">“Blood in the Water: The Attica Prison Uprising of 1971 and Its Legacy,” Heather Ann Thompson, Pantheon Books 2016 KNOPF DOUBLEDAY</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/ap_64693233018.jpg?w=728" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Inmates of the Attica Correctional Facility negotiating with Russell G. Oswald, lower left, the state prisons commissioner, in September 1971. ASSOCIATED PRESS</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/51jdxpa2axl.jpg?w=200" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">“The Turkey Shoot: Tracking the Attica Cover-up,” by Malcolm Bell, foreword by Tom Wicker, Grove Press 1985 (scheduled for re-release in March, 2017, with a new introduction and epilogue by the author as “The Attica Turkey Shoot: Justice On Trial.”) (pictured) SKYHORSE PUBLISHING</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/51bdfcba19l.jpg?w=200" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Uprising: Understanding Attica, Revolution and the Incarceration State, Clarence B. Jones and Stuart Connelly, Kindle Books 2011. AMAZON</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Roald Dahl at 100: A Reading List</title>
		<link>https://blog.longreads.com/2016/09/08/roald-dahl-100/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 15:27:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cheri Lucas Rowlands]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reading List]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roald Dahl]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.longreads.com/?p=38968</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Roald Dahl, the whimsical and wicked mind behind <em>Charlie and the Chocolate Factory</em>, <em>Matilda</em>, and other famous children's literature, would have turned 100 on September 13, 2016. Here are seven stories about the man behind these tales.<img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=38968&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When I was in elementary school in the eighties, being read to in class was such a treat &#8212; and something I really miss. The weekly reading hour that I looked forward to the most was when my favorite librarian came to read a few chapters from a Roald Dahl story. (And over the years, she read them <em>all</em>.) I could hardly wait to hear the next prank Mrs. Twit would play on Mr. Twit in <em>The Twits.</em> Another favorite, <em>The Witches,</em> remains one of the stories from my childhood that really opened me up to the magic of reading. Dahl&#8217;s whimsical yet macabre and darkly comic stories piqued my imagination for the first time in those years, and &#8212; being a shy, quiet kid &#8212; showed me that anything was possible.</p>
<p>September 13 is Roald Dahl&#8217;s birthday, and 2016 marks <a href="http://www.roalddahl.com/roalddahl100">100 years</a> since his birth. To celebrate, here are seven stories about the bestselling novelist, short story writer, screenwriter, fighter pilot, and British spy. <span id="more-38968"></span></p>
<h2>1. <a href="http://hazlitt.net/feature/great-missenden-plays-itself">&#8220;Great Missenden Plays Itself.&#8221;</a> (Michael Hingston, Hazlitt, August 2016)</h2>
<p>The village of Great Missenden in Buckinghamshire, a 45-minute train ride from London, is where Dahl lived for the last 35 years of his life. If you wander its streets, you&#8217;ll find that some of his most famous tales, from <em>The BFG</em> to <em>Matilda</em>, are set here.</p>
<h2>2. <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2014/aug/30/charlie-and-the-chocolate-factory-50-years-roald-dahl-quentin-blake">&#8220;Charlie and the Chocolate Factory at 50.&#8221;</a> (Lucy Mangan, The Guardian, August 2014)</h2>
<p>Mangan tells the story behind <em>Charlie and the Chocolate Factory</em>: how the book took shape, the state of the publishing industry and genre of children&#8217;s books at the time, and the evolution of the story on the screen and stage.</p>
<h2>3. <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/books/authors/roald-dahls-darkest-hour/">&#8220;Roald Dahl on the Death of His Daughter.&#8221;</a> (Donald Sturrock, The Telegraph, February 2015)</h2>
<p>In an edited excerpt of the biography <em>Storyteller: The Life of Roald Dahl</em>, Sturrock describes two family tragedies: an accident leaving his four-month-old son, Theo, with a shattered skull, later to develop hydrocephalus; and the death of his eldest daughter, Olivia, from measles encephalitis.</p>
<h2>4. <a href="http://thisrecording.com/today/2011/6/1/in-which-we-consider-the-macabre-unpleasantness-of-roald-dah.html">&#8220;In Which We Consider the Macabre Unpleasantness of Roald Dahl.&#8221;</a> (Alex Carnevale, This Recording, June 2011)</h2>
<p>&#8220;In everything good there is also something bad, and this was not only the theme Dahl took up in much of his work for both children and adults, but it was also true of him personally.&#8221; Carnevale chronicles the darker side of Dahl, the man.</p>
<h2>5. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/09/04/theater/roald-dahl-charlie-and-the-chocolate-factory.html">&#8220;Beyond &#8216;Wonka&#8217;: They Want Every Kid to Know Roald Dahl’s World.&#8221;</a> (Michael Paulson, The New York Times, August 2016)</h2>
<p>&#8220;With publishing shifting a lot, there is still, I think, a huge desire to bring his kind of vivid and mischievous world into other mediums&#8230;&#8221; Led by Dahl&#8217;s 30-year-old grandson, Luke Kelly, the Roald Dahl Literary Estate aims to introduce the author&#8217;s universe to a new generation of kids and transform itself into a story company for the digital age.</p>
<h2>6. <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2008/nov/09/felicity-dahl-roald">&#8220;My Years with Roald, by the &#8216;Love of His Life.’&#8221;</a> (Elizabeth Day, The Guardian, November 2008)</h2>
<p>Felicity Dahl, the author&#8217;s second wife (and with whom he had an 11-year affair during his first marriage to actress Patricia Neal), talks about their seven years together.</p>
<h2>7. <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/roald-dahls-twisted-overlooked-stories-for-adults">&#8220;Roald Dahl&#8217;s Twisted, Overlooked Stories for Adults.&#8221;</a> (David L. Ulin, The New Yorker, July 2016)</h2>
<p>&#8220;As with his books for children, his adult stories are marked by conscience, by a moral center that extends beyond mere payback, leading to moments of unexpected depth.&#8221; Ulin explores Dahl’s unconventional, lesser-known adult short stories.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=38968&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
		
		<media:thumbnail url="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/images-wigout-051916-roalddahl.jpg" />
		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/images-wigout-051916-roalddahl.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">images-wigout-051916-roalddahl</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://0.gravatar.com/avatar/36207d4c7c014b0999b995ca3971d383?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">CL</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>I Want to Know if Love is Real: Springsteen on His New Book, Born to Run</title>
		<link>https://blog.longreads.com/2016/09/07/i-want-to-know-if-love-is-real-springsteen-on-his-new-book-born-to-run/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 13:17:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Krista]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Editor's Pick]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Born to Run]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bruce Springsteen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interview]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[vanity fair]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.longreads.com/?p=39271</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[At Vanity Fair, David Kamp interviews Bruce Springsteen on his upbringing, depression, and the seeds of his upcoming book, 'Born to Run.'<img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39271&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Springsteen may today be a man who splits his time between a horse farm in his native Monmouth County, a second home in New Jersey, and luxury properties in Florida and L.A., but Born to Run is an emphatic refutation of the notion that, as a songwriter, he can no longer connect to the troubled and downtrodden. Especially in its early chapters, the book demonstrates how honestly Springsteen has come by his material. Cars, girls, the Shore, the workingman’s struggles, broken dreams, disillusioned vets—it’s all right there in his upbringing.</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>“One of the points I’m making in the book is that, whoever you’ve been and wherever you’ve been, it never leaves you,” he said, expanding upon this thought with the most Springsteen-esque metaphor possible: “I always picture it as a car. All your selves are in it. And a new self can get in, but the old selves can’t ever get out. The important thing is, who’s got their hands on the wheel at any given moment?”</p></blockquote>
<p>At <em><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/">Vanity Fair</a></em>, <a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/2016/09/bruce-springsteen-cover-story">David Kamp interviews Bruce Springsteen</a> on his upbringing, depression, and the seeds of his upcoming book, <em>Born to Run</em>.</p>
<p><a class="button-red" href="http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/2016/09/bruce-springsteen-cover-story?src=longreads">Read the story</a></p><img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39271&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
		
		<media:thumbnail url="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/3785989455_c953022522_b.jpg" />
		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/3785989455_c953022522_b.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">3785989455_c953022522_b</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/4f39e362b21c41df5cea83b50e4172fb?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kristastevens</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Choosing to Set Him Free: The Stillbirth of Charlie Showman</title>
		<link>https://blog.longreads.com/2016/09/06/choosing-to-set-him-free-the-stillbirth-of-charlie-showman/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2016 20:39:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Krista]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Editor's Pick]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[death]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pregnancy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stillbirth]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.longreads.com/?p=39126</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[At The Walrus, Georgina Blanchard reflects on the stillbirth of her son, Charlie Showman.<img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39126&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>My son was born in Toronto on September 15, 2010. He had dark, wet hair, and when I cradled him, he was warm and damp, swaddled in a flannel hospital sheet. He smelled just how you would think a newborn baby would smell. He had a pink, thin upper lip and a button nose. His eyes were closed, but the death certificate later said they were brown.</p></blockquote>
<p>At <em><a href="http://thewalrus.ca/">The Walrus</a></em>, <a href="http://thewalrus.ca/still-life/">Georgina Blanchard reflects</a> on the stillbirth of her son, Charlie Showman.  </p>
<p><a class="button-red" href="http://thewalrus.ca/still-life/?src=longreads">Read the story</a></p><img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39126&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
		
		<media:thumbnail url="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/4231898492_96ffeaf1f1_b.jpg" />
		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/4231898492_96ffeaf1f1_b.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">4231898492_96ffeaf1f1_b</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/4f39e362b21c41df5cea83b50e4172fb?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kristastevens</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Pleasures of Protest: Taking on Gentrification in Chinatown</title>
		<link>https://blog.longreads.com/2016/09/06/the-pleasures-of-protest-taking-on-gentrification-in-chinatown/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2016 11:24:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Esther Wang]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[personal essay]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CAAAV]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chinatown]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Esther Wang]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gentrification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jacob Riis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jane Jacobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Karen Ishikuza]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York City]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peter Kwong]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.longreads.com/?p=38299</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Working as a tenant organizer in New York's Chinatown opened Esther Wang's eyes to the ugly—and complicated—realities of gentrification in New York City.<img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=38299&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align:center;"><i><a href="http://www.estherwang.com/">Esther Wang</a> | Longreads | August 2016 | 17 minutes (4,223 words)</i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>On a cold night in the early winter months of 2007, I was with a group of tenants — all Latino and Chinese immigrant families — clustered together in front of their home, two buildings on Delancey Street that straddled the border between Chinatown and the Lower East Side. We were there, shivering in the cold, to protest their landlords. </p>
<p>Ever since they bought the two buildings in 2001, the owners of 55 Delancey and 61 Delancey Street — Nir Sela, Michael Daniel, and 55 Delancey Street Realty LLC — had been attempting to kick out the Chinese and Latino families who had lived there, but in recent months, the situation had come to a head. They had begun aggressively bringing tenants to housing court, often on trumped up charges (one lawsuit argued that, based on the number of shoes displayed inside the apartment, it was obvious that more than just one family lived there); offered several families significant buyouts to leave; and had refused to make basic repairs. For stretches at a time, and in the coldest days of winter, there had been no heat or hot water. </p>
<p>That evening, huddled in our winter coats and clutching hand-made signs, we waited for the arrival of one of the owners, who had agreed to meet with us and discuss our demands. </p>
<p>I had been volunteering with <a href="http://caaav.org/">CAAAV</a>, a tenant organizing group in Chinatown, and in the months prior, I had spent many of my nights going from apartment to apartment, often with Zhi Qin Zheng, a resident of the building as well as an organizer at CAAAV, helping to painstakingly document their living conditions and assisting residents in calling the city’s 311 hotline so that each housing code violation would be on record. </p>
<p>Their apartments were cramped, even rundown, but for these families, it was home, and they wanted to stay. Over the years, each building had become a small community, one where people felt comfortable leaving their doors open and asking each other to watch their children. “If we left, where would we go?” Sau Ying Kwok, a feisty grandmother with a nimbus of frizzy hair, wondered aloud. She had become one of the more vocal leaders in the building, along with the soft-spoken You Liu Lin, a man in his middle years with a penchant for Brylcreeming his hair as well as shoving bottles of water and perfect Fuji apples into my hands whenever I knocked on his door. </p>
<p>I often questioned why I was there on those trips. I had moved to the city three years prior from Texas, fresh out of college and possessing a vague notion that I would put my Asian American Studies degree to use and, in the words of 1960s radicals inspired by Mao Zedong, “serve the people.” <span id="more-38299"></span></p>
<blockquote class="pullquote center"><p> I felt a complicated sense of belonging that I had never experienced before, complicated because I was, in many ways, an outsider…</p></blockquote>
<p>In a way, I was continuing the tradition of those who were part of the Asian American movement of the 1960s — young, mostly college-educated Chinese, Japanese, and Filipino Americans who not only coined the term “Asian American” but also immersed themselves in ethnic enclaves like Chinatown on the east and west coasts. </p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B00N6PCO4Q/"><em>Serve The People: Making Asian America in the Long Sixties</em></a>, her book chronicling the Asian American movement, Karen Ishizuka wrote that people had to become Asian American. It wasn’t about your ethnic background, but “a political identity developed out of the oppositional consciousness of the Long Sixties, in order to be seen and heard.” </p>
<p>But there has always been a disconnect between these Asian American activists and the people they served, who tended to be primarily working-class immigrants, a disconnect that I felt keenly. What was I, an ABC (American-born Chinese) doing in a mostly immigrant community, with my barely passable Mandarin? I didn’t really know, but I felt a complicated sense of belonging that I had never experienced before, complicated because I was, in many ways, an outsider — someone not from the neighborhood or embedded in its history, who wasn’t threaded through the day-to-day life that makes a grouping of city blocks a community. Yet the residents didn’t treat me as an outsider when they invited me into their homes; being Chinese, it seemed, was enough.</p>
<p>It was easy to understand why the owners would want to wholesale evict these families, who all lived in rent-stabilized apartments where rents were, on average, $1000 or less, far below what the owners could charge in the hot real estate market of lower Manhattan, where people fought for the right to pay $3000 a month for a two-bedroom apartment.</p>
<p>That night, I got a lesson in what some have called the pleasures of protest. When Nir Sela and his wife arrived and saw the mass of people waiting for them on the sidewalk, when they saw the cameras, they quickly turned around and walked away. We began following them, scores of people chanting, “Shame on you! Shame on you!” They quickly got into a cab and sped away. Despite the abrupt cancellation of the meeting we had planned, everyone seemed pleased, smiles on their faces. </p>
<p>Soon after, the tenants decided to go on a rent strike. It was a success — a few months later, the owners capitulated, agreeing to make all the necessary repairs and to end eviction proceedings, along with a payment of $3000 to each household. Less than a year later, I would join the staff of CAAAV as a full-time housing organizer, still high off the success of that campaign victory.</p>
<p>But in a city where finance capital reigns, this sense of victory wouldn’t last for long. </p>
<p style="text-align:center;">* * *</p>
<p>Chinatown as we know it today didn’t really exist until the 1970s, when, in the wake of the 1965 Immigration Act, Chinese immigrants began arriving in large numbers.</p>
<p>Yet as early as the 1850s, one could find a small bachelor community of Chinese men living in what was then known as Five Points (and what some today have called “America’s first slum”), a neighborhood that had arisen on top of a landfill whose residents were free blacks as well as Irish, Jewish, and Italian immigrants. Jacob Riis in his influential 1890 book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/How-Other-Half-Lives-Tenements/dp/1420925032/"><em>How the Other Half Lives: Studies Among the Tenements of New York</em></a>, devoted an entire chapter to Chinatown, writing dismissively, “Chinatown as a spectacle is disappointing. Next door to the Bend, it has little of its outdoor stir and life, none of its gayly-colored rags or picturesque filth and poverty.” Yet the neighborhood, he noted, had already taken on the tinge of the exotic, New Yorkers believing it was rife with far more opium dens than actually existed. </p>
<blockquote class="pullquote center"><p> People expressed a lot of strange beliefs about Chinatown, ideas that became increasingly more bizarre to me the more time I spent in the neighborhood.</p></blockquote>
<p>The black residents fled after an anti-abolition riot; the Chinese men, sailors as well as workers who had moved from the west coast in the wake of increasingly oppressive laws and racist mob violence, stayed because they had nowhere else to go. “Residents of New York Chinatown could not cross Canal Street into Little Italy without the risk of being beaten up;” wrote John Kuo Wei Tchen, the historian and founder of the Museum of Chinese in America, “laundry men in the scattered boroughs and suburbs illegally lived in the back of their shops because they could not rent apartments.” </p>
<p>By the early 1960s, there were only 5,000 residents of Chinatown, mostly elderly men who lived on the blocks clustered around Columbus Park. The neighborhood surrounding it was in decline, the Irish having moved away decades prior, and the Jewish and Italian immigrants who had come to define the Lower East Side having already begun fleeing in rapid numbers. </p>
<p>Without the 1965 Immigration Act, Chinatown would have faded away. But as tens of thousands of immigrants began flocking to New York City, the empty tenements and boarded up storefronts filled with families and small businesses, and the old garment factories once again hummed with the sound of sewing machines, this time manned by a workforce of Chinese immigrant women. Chinatown mushroomed over the next two decades, spreading until it was bordered by Soho and Tribeca to the west and the East River on the opposite end, with Delancey Street settled as the line delineating Chinatown from the Lower East Side. </p>
<p>According to the scholar Peter Kwong, this expansion ended by the mid-1990s, halted by the revitalization of the neighborhoods bordering Chinatown. The events of 9/11 further destabilized the neighborhood, located as it was so close to the Financial District, but, <a href="http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/09/17/answers-about-the-gentrification-of-chinatown-part-2/">as Kwong put it in the <em>New York Times</em></a>: “The root cause of the decline of Chinatown predated the 9/11 attack; the collapse of the garment industry and years of harm done by real estate speculation had already taken their toll on the community.” </p>
<p>I didn’t know any of this history when I came to New York City in 2004 and moved into an apartment in central Harlem, itself a neighborhood in flux, where I paid $750 each month to live with two roommates. Like most, all I knew was that Chinatown had a lot of Chinese people, and that fact alone drew me to the neighborhood on evenings after work and on weekends. Having grown up in south Texas, I had moved in large part out of a desire to live somewhere where I could feel a sense of belonging that I hadn’t had as a child. </p>
<p>People expressed a lot of strange beliefs about Chinatown, ideas that became increasingly more bizarre to me the more time I spent in the neighborhood. It’s often described as “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/04/03/realestate/the-lower-east-side-gritty-meets-trendy.html">gritty</a>” or “<a href="https://www.renthop.com/study/new-york-city-ny/chinatown-article.html">dirty</a>,” or as “exotic.” Other commonly used descriptors are “authentic” and “unchanging.”</p>
<p>Those descriptions made me cringe, not only for the casual racism underpinning them and, in the words of the scholar Lisa Lowe in her book Immigrant Acts, “the gaze that seeks to exoticize [Chinatown] as antiquated artifact”, but because they miss an essential truth of the neighborhood — that what is thought of as exotic or authentic to some, is simply the minutiae of life for others. I often observed people, usually tourists, who came to the neighborhood expecting some sort of ethnic theme park, and who were confused when instead they found a neighborhood that, like most, was a mixture of both quotidian pleasures and the mundane. (Case in point: a white family I once observed, standing on the corner of Essex and Hester Streets, right next to a dumpling stall. “But where’s Chinatown?” one of them asked, confused.)</p>
<blockquote class="pullquote center"><p> I realized that long-time residents have a map in their minds of the places they live in that others lack. An empty loft building on Bowery that to me had the potential to become a future condo development, was for her the former garment factory where she had worked.</p></blockquote>
<p>And yet I too was guilty of a sort of fetishization, for I had my own foolish, romantic notions of the neighborhood, tinged with a nostalgia for a home I had never had. Eating dumplings wasn’t just a meal — it was embracing my culture. During the four years that I worked in the neighborhood, these notions were quickly disabused by the everyday life and reality that I saw around me. I began to understand that Chinatown was a vibrant neighborhood of the present, the kind that urban planning writer and activist Jane Jacobs described as displaying the “exuberant diversity” that she believed characterized the best cities, the ones that thrived. </p>
<p>I saw this most on display on the days I would accompany Zhi Qin Zheng to do outreach at Sara D. Roosevelt Park, the neighborhood’s central gathering place, a narrow, rectangular strip of a park shaded by the crowded tenement buildings that ringed it on both sides. On a typical day, it was packed – young families with their kids filling the playground, teenagers playing games of handball on the courts to the north, packs of middle-aged men standing around chain smoking. Everybody who lived and worked in Chinatown passed through this park, known in Mandarin as Grand Park for the busy thoroughfare that bisected it from east to west. </p>
<p>Residents like Ms. Zheng didn’t see their neighborhood as “authentic” or “unchanging.” A former garment worker who lost her job after the 9/11 attacks led to the closure of most of the garment factories in the neighborhood, Ms. Zheng knew intimately the struggles that residents of the neighborhood faced, not only from her years spent battling her own landlord, but from all the tenants who came to us every week during our office hours with eviction notices in their hands. </p>
<p>Was Chinatown gentrifying? Some didn’t think so. According to a <em>New York Magazine</em> <a href="http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2015/09/how-has-chinatown-stayed-chinatown.html">article published in September, 2015</a>, “Chinatown has largely resisted the laws of the real estate market,” despite occupying “one of the most desirable tracts of real estate in all of Manhattan.”</p>
<p>Yet the numbers told a different story. Census numbers show that the Chinese population of the neighborhood declined by 17 percent between 2000 and 2010, and according to NYU’s Furman Center, median rents in Chinatown had climbed from an average of $745 per month in 2005 to $946 just five years later, with newer residents paying upwards of $1500 per month. </p>
<p>For me, my work in the neighborhood was the way I actualized my political ideals; for Ms. Zheng, it was survival, nurtured by her belief, born from experience, that tenants could win. Together, we spent countless hours trudging up and down the streets of Chinatown, handing out brochures and flyers and talking to residents about gentrification. In these interactions, I often deferred to Ms. Zheng, a compact woman in her late 50s with a no-nonsense bob and tanned skin who spoke three Chinese dialects fluently, who could connect with other immigrant residents in a way that I couldn’t. As we walked, I would ask her questions about the neighborhood, and it was through her that I realized that long-time residents have a map in their minds of the places they live in that others lack. An empty loft building on Bowery that to me had the potential to become a future condo development, was for her the former garment factory where she had worked. </p>
<p>I began to understand that gentrification, which was so often described as white people moving into a neighborhood and displacing long-time residents, was actually a process that was far more complex. Was I myself a gentrifier? I had often asked myself that question, having first lived in Harlem and then later on, in Bed-Stuy, long-standing black communities whose blackness and affordability were being swept away by the same forces that were turning Chinatown into an extension of Soho or the Lower East Side, its small businesses replaced by art galleries and cocktail bars. The incongruity of my work in Chinatown with my presence in these neighborhoods struck me as an unresolvable contradiction, one where I was caught up in the zero sum game that is the housing market in New York City, a game that I didn’t want to play but couldn’t opt out of.</p>
<p>And yet, it was much easier to believe that gentrification was about individual people making the choice to move into a neighborhood versus the reality — that it was about capital and who had it; about laws and systems that were stacked against tenants; that private property was king, and always had been. </p>
<p>We were too often confusing the visible symptoms for the cause. Maybe it felt good and even righteous to sneer at these urban pioneers moving in with their CB2 sofas and their love for cold brew coffee, but the recent arrivals I met on those nights going from building to building and knocking on doors, who admittedly fit the description of a gentrifier — white, young, college-educated — weren’t the problem, though they could be startlingly obtuse (one complained to me about the smells emanating from her neighbor’s apartment). They needed a place to live, after all. I guess I did, too. But so did the residents of Chinatown, and for them, there was rarely the option of moving to another gentrifying neighborhood. They depended on their rent-stabilized apartments. Once they were forced out, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/07/08/realestate/rent-stabilized-apartments-ever-more-elusive.html?pagewanted=all">their chances of finding another rent-stabilized apartment were practically nil</a>, and if they did happen to find one out of sheer luck or connections, the rent would most likely be much higher. </p>
<p>Chinatown was a place layered with Ms. Zheng’s history and that of the people who had built the neighborhood over decades. It was this history and her version of the neighborhood that needed to be saved, not mine, and in the summer of 2008, she would have to fight for her home and the homes of her neighbors one more time, for the two buildings on Delancey Street would once again be, as a news article put it, the focus of the “gentrification wars” that were raging in the neighborhood. </p>
<p style="text-align:center;">* * *</p>
<p>For a time, it seemed as if everyone, not only in New York but in cities around the country, was talking about gentrification. A new national coalition called Right to the City had launched at the inaugural United States Social Forum in 2007, inspired by the writings of the French Marxist Henri Lefebvre. Their name came from what Lefebvre called the “right to the city,” a “transformed and renewed right to urban life” possessed “firstly of all [by] those who inhabit.” For Lefebvre as well as his contemporary Jane Jacobs, the planning of city neighborhoods should be in the hands of their residents, who they believed were the ones who knew best what kind of development was needed.</p>
<p>They were heady words, thrilling words. Yet radical politics meant little to most residents of Chinatown and to the tenants of 55 and 61 Delancey, who simply wanted to be able to stay in their homes.</p>
<p>In the spring of 2008, less than a year after the successful rent strike at 55 and 61 Delancey, residents of the two buildings began calling us and coming to our office on Hester Street, bringing letters that said the buildings were under new management. A few months earlier, they had been sold (again!) for $20 million to the real estate investment firm Madison Capital, whose slick website described the two buildings as an “underperforming” asset, one in which they would commence a “repositioning strategy” that would focus on the “renovation and releasing of under market residential apartments.”</p>
<blockquote class="pullquote center"><p> I was constantly going to housing court, whose hallways were invariably packed with black, Latino, and Asian tenants. I rarely saw a white person who wasn’t an attorney.</p></blockquote>
<p>We soon learned what their “repositioning strategy” entailed, some of which was already familiar to the families who lived at 55 and 61 Delancey Street — delaying repairs in order to frustrate residents into leaving, resulting in leaky ceilings that went unfixed to the point that some began caving in, or taking days to fix the hot water that suddenly stopped working; taking tenants to court, where they would have to prove that they did in fact live there; and offering buyouts of up to $60,000. Other tactics were new, and meant to deliberately harass the Chinese residents in the buildings — at one point at the end of 2008, someone went around and tore down the red and gold Lunar New Year decorations that many families taped to their doors, and shortly after, the management company barred them from putting them back up, claiming they were fire hazards (a Christmas wreath adorning the exterior of a market-rate apartment, however, was allowed to remain). </p>
<p>Yet much of what Madison Capital had done wasn’t illegal; as for the rest, we would have to take the private equity firm to court to prove that it was harassment, using a new law passed just a few months earlier by the city council (previously, harassment wasn’t considered a local housing law violation). The families on Delancey Street once again would have to mobilize. </p>
<p>From the outset, it became clear that Madison Capital — whose lawyer, in a curious twist, was Candace Sela, the previous owner’s wife — would go to greater lengths than the previous landlords had in their efforts to push people out, going so far as to accuse one of the tenants, Ding Juan Zhang, of being a prostitute in the court papers they filed to evict her. At one of the first organizing meetings we held, crowded on the second floor landing of one of the buildings, we were suddenly interrupted by a police officer, responding to a 911 call from the superintendent who claimed we were causing a disturbance. The lawyer who was there with us argued that we were merely exercising our First Amendment rights, that we were breaking no laws by meeting. I tried to placate the officer, a young Asian man, promising we would be quiet. After that, he left, and we continued our meeting; this would happen two more times in the following months. </p>
<p>In January of 2010, a year after we filed the lawsuit, the case was settled. We had technically won, but it felt hollow. Some of the families, tired of constantly having to battle a revolving door of landlords, chose to move away, and how could anyone blame them for leaving? Every time I went to the building, it seemed as if someone new was moving in. </p>
<p>Meanwhile, in the same time period, tenants had been evicted wholesale from 81 Bowery, a single room occupancy building, after city inspectors found it ridden with housing violations. I was constantly going to housing court, whose hallways were invariably packed with black, Latino, and Asian tenants. I rarely saw a white person who wasn’t an attorney. A fire destroyed the Hong Kong Supermarket on East Broadway and Pike Street, and it was announced that a hotel would be built in its place. Another local supermarket, the Pathmark on Cherry Street, shuttered its doors, and it was rumored that it would be replaced by a 72-story luxury condo building. The former site of the Music Palace Theater, a Chinese-language theater which closed in 1998, became a gleaming new Wyndham hotel. </p>
<p>It was hard not to feel that we were engaged in a Sisyphean task, trying to staunch the blood flowing from a thousands gaping wounds with the tiniest of Band-Aids.</p>
<p>Shortly after Superstorm Sandy hit, I left New York City and Chinatown for Beijing, fleeing the neighborhood that I both loved and had begun to despair would be able to remain. Each tenant and family that moved away, each supermarket that then turned into a hotel, was a hammer that chipped away at my now-tenuous belief that the neighborhood could somehow escape the forces of change that had overtaken so much of the city.</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">* * *</p>
<p>It’s trendy these days to opine that <a href="http://nymag.com/news/features/gentrification-2014-2/">gentrification isn’t all that bad</a>, or that <a href="http://nymag.com/scienceofus/2016/04/is-everyone-focusing-too-much-on-gentrification.html">it’s misunderstood</a>. Some even argue that <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2015/01/the_gentrification_myth_it_s_rare_and_not_as_bad_for_the_poor_as_people.html">it’s a myth</a>, or that it actually <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2015/11/12/news/economy/gentrification-may-help-poor-people/">benefits poor people</a>. </p>
<p>I suspect that these articles are mostly written by people who have never had their heat turned off in the dead of winter or been offered a buyout to leave their home, people who have never received a frantic phone call from someone late at night saying that they’re being told to move out immediately and that they don’t know what to do and have no place to go. The toll of this type of displacement can never be fully told by the statistics that are duly trotted out in these articles. What I learned in those years I spent in Chinatown is that you need to measure it by each family that is forced out, each change that weakens the vitality of a place that has been created over decades. </p>
<p>There is a lot of handwringing over the future of Chinatown, whose Chinese population is now third in size to Flushing and Sunset Park. To some, change is inevitable. Chinatown is, after all, itself the product of new immigrants coming in and filling the vacuum left behind by others. But not all change carries equal weight. The Chinatown of the past and present, a place where generations of immigrants have been able to add their own imprint, a place where layers of history commingle and coexist all at once? It’s that neighborhood that is disappearing.</p>
<p>Recently, I went back to 55 and 61 Delancey Street, where I spent so many of my evenings in my twenties. The surrounding blocks, now boasting two oyster bars and a smattering of coffeeshops, had changed, and so had the two buildings, where empty apartments were now being rented for upwards of $4000 per month. </p>
<p>At the end of 2012, right after I had left New York City, 55 and 61 Delancey had swapped hands yet again, this time being sold for $50 million as part of a package that included buildings in Soho and the West Village. After the sale, another wave of evictions had begun, furthered along by Misidor LLC, a firm that specializes in helping “management companies and property owners to buy out and relocate low-rent tenants” and “identify and vacate illegal tenants.” Misidor’s website, before it was shuttered in 2014 by the Attorney General for the company’s role in harassing residents of rent-stabilized apartments, boasted that it had succeeded in relocating “hundreds of tenants.”</p>
<p>I was curious if any of the people I had worked with remained — the sharp-tongued Sau Ying Kwok; You Liu Lin; Ding Juan Zhang. The carpet was new, and the walls were freshly painted, as were the doors to each home, now done in a matte dark grey. And those tenants I remembered, who had fought for years for the right to claim a piece of New York City their own?</p>
<p>Ms. Kwok still lived there, but the rest? They were gone.</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">* * *</p>
<p style="text-align:center;"><em>Esther Wang is a writer based in New York City. Follow her on Twitter at <em><a href="https://twitter.com/estherxlwang">@estherxlwang</a></em></p>
<p style="text-align:center;"><em>Editor: <a href="http://twitter.com/saribotton">Sari Botton</a></em></p><img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=38299&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
		
		<media:thumbnail url="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/08/chinatown31.jpg" />
		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/08/chinatown31.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">chinatown3</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://0.gravatar.com/avatar/011556e60fa2879038ce1bf74ff1c8ae?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">estherxlwang</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Back To School: A Reading List</title>
		<link>https://blog.longreads.com/2016/09/05/back-to-school-a-reading-list/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 20:15:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Emily Perper]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reading List]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[BuzzFeed]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chronicle of higher education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Los Angeles Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reading list]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Big Roundtable]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Billfold]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.longreads.com/?p=39036</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Bullies, teachers, classmates—it's time to head back to school with these six stories from the The Big Roundtable, Los Angeles Times, and more.<img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39036&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Bullies, teachers, classmates—it&#8217;s time to head back to school with these six stories from the Chronicle of Higher Education, Los Angeles Times and more.</p>
<h2>1. <a href="http://www.thebigroundtable.com/stories/twice-exceptional/">&#8220;Twice Exceptional.&#8221;</a> (Hana Schank, The Big Roundtable, July 2015)</h2>
<p>Hana Schank navigates a disturbingly complex bureaucracy to advocate for her four-year-old daughter, Nora, who is exceptionally bright and low-vision. <span id="more-39036"></span></p>
<h2>2. <a href="https://thebillfold.com/out-of-pocket-what-teachers-across-the-country-spend-on-supplies-5e6b855856fd#.ct5s664j6">&#8220;Out of Pocket: What Teachers Across the Country Spend on Supplies.&#8221;</a> (Joanna Petrone, The Billfold, August 2016)</h2>
<p>Teaching is grueling—emotionally, physically and financially. My mom is a librarian/media specialist at a public elementary school, and she works hard year-round to make her media center beautiful. While she&#8217;s reimbursed for some of the books she purchases, other items&#8211;like the colorful rugs, decor and pirate-ship playhouse in the reading corner&#8211;come out of her own paycheck. At The Billfold, teachers from across the country share which supplies they pay for out-of-pocket, and the numbers are shocking.</p>
<h2>3. <a href="https://www.buzzfeed.com/shannonkeating/coming-out-as-gay-in-elementary-school?utm_term=.pvLBNXD3W#.vtNkPEJZr">&#8220;Coming Out as Gay in Elementary School.&#8221;</a> (Shannon Keating, BuzzFeed News, April 2015)</h2>
<p>Kids are coming out younger and younger, whether they&#8217;re exploring their gender identity and expression or sexual orientation. The adolescents, families and experts profiled in this piece have great advice for creating affirming, supportive spaces.</p>
<h2>4. <a href="http://www.insidecolumbia.net/2013/04/01/schools-out-forever/?cparticle=3&amp;siarticle=2&amp;src=longreads">&#8220;School&#8217;s Out Forever.&#8221;</a> (Allison Pohle, Inside Columbia Magazine, April 2013)</h2>
<p>Unschooled kids aren&#8217;t only in hippie enclaves. Meet the Missouri families letting their kids take the reins of their education.</p>
<h2>5. <a href="http://www.latimes.com/projects/la-me-framed/#chapter1">&#8220;Framed.&#8221;</a> (Christopher Goffard, Los Angeles Times, September 2016)</h2>
<p>A tale of two bullies, neither of the playground or cyber variety: Two highly educated lawyers decided to make the life of the PTA president a living hell.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39036&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
		
		<media:thumbnail url="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/8314450897_1d88ebf7c0_o.jpg" />
		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/8314450897_1d88ebf7c0_o.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">buses</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/50bd3faf41be155829d0abf3b8b02119?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">emilyperper</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Top 5 Longreads of the Week</title>
		<link>https://blog.longreads.com/2016/09/02/the-top-5-longreads-of-the-week-134/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2016 19:21:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Longreads]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Top 5]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[longreads]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top 5]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.longreads.com/?p=39000</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Our top stories of the week, as chosen by the editors at Longreads.<img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39000&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Below, our favorite stories of the week.</em></p>
<p><em><a href="http://longreads.us2.list-manage2.com/subscribe?u=1854296747731744c923a33ef&amp;id=bd2ad42066">Sign up to receive this list free every Friday in your inbox.</a></em><span id="more-39000"></span></p>
<p style="text-align:center;">* * *</p>
<h2 class="top5-title"><a href="http://www.gq.com/story/inside-federal-bureau-of-way-too-many-guns?src=longreads" target="_blank">1. Inside the Federal Bureau of Way Too Many Guns</a></h2>
<p class="top5-credit"><em>Jeanne Marie Laskas | GQ | Aug. 30, 2016 | 27 minutes (6,922 words)</em></p>
<p style="text-align:left;">A sobering behind-the-scenes look at the antiquated system for tracing gun ownership in America.</p>
<h2 class="top5-title"><a href="http://www.latimes.com/projects/la-me-framed/?src=longreads" target="_blank">2. Framed</a></h2>
<p class="top5-credit"><em>Christopher Goffard | Los Angeles Times | Sept. 2, 2016 | 51 minutes (12,956 words)</em></p>
<p>A six-part series unraveling the story of a suburban PTA mom who was framed for drugs.</p>
<h2 class="top5-title"><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/09/04/magazine/edward-snowdens-long-strange-journey-to-hollywood.html?src=longreads" target="_blank">3. Edward Snowden&#8217;s Long, Strange Journey to Hollywood</a></h2>
<p class="top5-credit"><em>Irina Aleksander | New York Times | August 30, 2016 | 32 minutes (8,018 words) </em></p>
<p>A behind-the-scenes look at how Oliver Stone&#8217;s &#8220;Snowden&#8221; got made.</p>
<h2 class="top5-title"><a href="http://www.esquire.com/news-politics/a48039/rich-wilkerson-pastor-kanye-west-kim-kardashian/?src=longreads" target="_blank">4. The Ministry of Fun</a></h2>
<p class="top5-credit"><em>Jeff Sharlet | Esquire | August 30, 2016 | 21 minutes (5,286 words) </em></p>
<p>Celebrities, skinny jeans, reality TV ─ Pastor Rich Wilkerson Jr. has it all, including DJs working the baptism. This is the new breed of Capitalist America&#8217;s pastors.</p>
<h2 class="top5-title"><a href="http://www.wired.com/2016/08/jerry-hayes-how-to-save-the-bees-monsanto/" target="_blank">5. A Swarm of Controversy</a></h2>
<p class="top5-credit"><em>Hannah Nordhaus | Wired | August 26, 2016 | 17 minutes (4,539 words)</em></p>
<p>In their struggle for survival against killer mites, bees get an unlikely ally: Monsanto.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=39000&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
		
		<media:thumbnail url="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/filing-cabinets-e1472841159741.png" />
		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/filing-cabinets-e1472841159741.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">FILING CABINETS</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/77c994c441138efdb7338403caac1014?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">longreadseditors</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Duality of &#8216;Home,&#8217; or, a Life Both Lived and On Display</title>
		<link>https://blog.longreads.com/2016/09/01/the-duality-of-home-or-a-life-both-lived-and-on-display/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 16:47:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michelle W.]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Domesticity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[identity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interior design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[new york times magazine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rachel Cusk]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.longreads.com/?p=38979</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In The New York Times Magazine, Rachel Cusk meditates on the ways our homes are simultaneously the places we live, and set pieces that we art-direct.<img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=38979&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>In Italy once, I was given a private tour of a beautiful castle, led by the owner through room after impeccably furnished room, only to glimpse at the end through a half-open door a tiny, cavelike space crammed with all the evidence — a gas stove, a television, a tatty sofa — of daily life: This was clearly where the family spent their time. I have often looked at photographs of writers in their elegant book-lined studies and marveled at what seems to me a mirage of sorts, the near-perfect alignment of seeming with being, the convincing illusion of mental processes on public display, as though writing a book were not the work of someone capable of all the shame and deviousness and coldheartedness in the world.</p></blockquote>
<p>&#8212; In <em>The New York Times Magazine</em>, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/09/04/magazine/making-house-notes-on-domesticity.html?_r=0">Rachel Cusk meditates</a> on the ways our homes are simultaneously the places we live, and set pieces that we art-direct.</p>
<p><a class="button-red" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/09/04/magazine/making-house-notes-on-domesticity.html?_r=0">Read the essay</a></p><img alt="" border="0" src="https://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=blog.longreads.com&#038;blog=70135762&#038;post=38979&#038;subd=longreadsblog&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
		
		<media:thumbnail url="https://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/08/living-room.jpeg" />
		<media:content url="http://longreadsblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/08/living-room.jpeg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">living room</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/2367004060918e221dcb9799584e9279?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Michelle, Communications</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
